The Life Of Muhammadﷺ, The Makkan Period,
by Imam Anwar Al-Awlaki,
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝
Few months after, the end of the embargo.
About six months later
the man who has supported the Messenger of Allah ﷺ
was now, on his deathbed leaving this world.
Abu Talib(أبو طالب) was dying and Muhammadﷺ was on his side
and the Messenger of Allah ﷺ told his Uncle, يَا عَمْ O uncle, Say;
لا اله الا الله
Say that there is no God but Allah, give me this word so that I can witness for you on the Day of Judgment.
Give me something in my hand so that I could argue on your behalf on the Day of Judgment.
All what I want from you is to say;
لا اله الا الله
Sitting on the other side, was who?
Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل)
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), it's amazing, wherever you go in Seerah(سيرة), you would find this man in front of you,
causing problems leading in evil.
Wherever you go in Seerah(سيرة), you'll just have Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) standing right there in front of you.
He was relentless in his efforts to fight Rasool Allah ﷺ, he did not give up until the last moment.
Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) and Abdullah Bin Abi Umayyah(عبدالله بن ابي امية) were sitting on the other side.
Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) interjected and said,
O Ibn Abdul Muttalib(ابن عبدالمطلب) are you going to die
on a religion other than the religion of Abdul Muttalib(عبدالمطلب)?
Are you going to denounce the religion of your father?
Rasool Allah ﷺ repeated again.
O my uncle say;
لا اله الا الله
And Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) continued interrupting
and then it went on until about Abu Talib(ابو طالب) pronounced his last words. He said:
بَلْ عَلَى مِلَّة عَبْدَ الْمُطَّلِبْ
I am dying on the religion of my father, Abdul Muttalib(عبدالمطلب).
Those were his last words.
This narration by the way that I mentioned to you is in Al-Bukhari(البخاريْ), there's another narration in Muslim(مسلم).
Let's first finish this narration of Al-Bukhari(البخاريْ).
So, Abu Talib(أبو طالب) passed away.
The Messenger of Allah, Muhammadﷺ said:
I'm going to continue asking Allah to forgive him.
Unless I'm provident from doing so.
I'm going to keep on asking Allah to forgive my uncle.
You know, that was a very, very difficult moment on Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Remember Abu Talib(أبوطالب) was the one, who raised up Muhammadﷺ,
he sponsored him, he took care of him at the age of eight.
So, he was the one caring for him, in his childhood
and then he's the one who stood beside him in his adulthood.
And Abu Talib(ابو طالب) was supporting, defending, protecting Muhammadﷺ for over 42 years.
It started at the age of eight,
and it went on, until Rasool Allah ﷺ was at the age of 50.
So, we can say that Abu Talib(ابو طالب) has spent most of his time in defense of Muhammadﷺ.
So, it was an extremely difficult time for Muhammad صلوات الله وسلام عليه to see that his dear uncle is dying as a disbelievers.
So, Muhammadﷺ said: I'm gonna ask Allah to forgive him.
And he asked Allah to forgive him, until Allah revealed the verse.
مَا كَانَ لِلنَّبِيِّ وَالَّذِينَ آمَنُوا أَنْ يَسْتَغْفِرُوا لِلْمُشْرِكِينَ وَلَوْ
وَلَوْ كَانُوا أُولِي قُرْبَىٰ مِنْ بَعْدِ مَا تَبَيَّنَ لَهُمْ أَنَّهُمْ أَصْحَابُ الْجَحِيمِ۝
It is not fitting for the Prophet and those who believe that they should invoke Allah for forgiveness for pagans,
even though they be of kin, after it has become clear to them, that they are companions of the Fire.
It is not allowed for you to seek forgiveness for somebody who died on disbelief.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was forbidden from doing that.
In this narration by Muslim(مسلم), Rasool Allah ﷺ was telling his uncle to say;
لا اله الا الله
His uncle responded by saying
if it were not for Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), insulting me and saying that it was only fear of death that made me say it,
I would do so and please you.
Abu Talib(ابو طالب) knew that it would please Muhammadﷺ,
he knew how much it would hurt the Messenger of Allah to know that his uncle died as disbelievers.
So, Abu Talib(ابو طالب), Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), he was even sympathetic to Muhammadﷺ in this case.
He said I would have said it, just to please you,
but I don't want the news to get out to the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
that I did it out of fear of dying.
So, it was a matter of honor and dignity for him.
Not to say it, and that's when Allahسبحانه وتعالى revealed the verse,
إِنَّكَ لَا تَهْدِي مَنْ أَحْبَبْتَ وَلَٰكِنَّ اللَّهَ يَهْدِي مَنْ يَشَاءُ ۚ
You cannot give guidance to those, whom you love,
but it is Allah Who gives guidance to the ones He wills.
So, guidance is not in the hands of anyone except Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
even the Prophet of Allah, his mission is to convey the message and not to convert,
converting the heart of a person is in the hands of Allah, not in the hands of people.
And therefore in Islam coercion in faith is not allowed,
لَا إِكْرَاهَ فِي الدِّينِ ۖ
There's no coercion in religion,
because this is something beyond our ability,
you cannot coerce something on the heart of a person.
So, it should be a matter of choice by people they have the freedom to choose their faith.
And that is how they would be held accountable in front of Allahسبحانه وتعالى,
it is because of that freedom that they have.
So, now Rasool Allah ﷺ is dealing with this tragic event that happened to him,
two months later, Khadijahرضي الله عنها dies.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is still dealing with the death of his Uncle
and here his dear wife, the most beloved person to him, passes away.
This year was called Aam-El-Huzn(عام الحزن), the year of sorrow.
And this was the 10th year after Rasool Allah ﷺ received revelation.
It was the most tragic time on Muhammadﷺ
because he lost the most two influential persons in supporting his message.
Khadijahرضي الله عنها, who offered Rasool Allah ﷺ with psychological support,
in addition to financial support due to her business
and Abu Talib(ابو طالب), who offered Muhammadﷺ with physical support.
So, suddenly these two pillars which he was standing on, collapsed.
So, this year is not called the year of tragedy, the year of sorrow,
just because Rasool Allah ﷺ lost two dear people,
but also because it was such a setback to the preaching of the message.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, who had freedom in going around preaching the message
was now being blocked because his uncle passed away.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ, who would go home to find comfort with his wife Khadijah(خديجه), would go home and find no one.
Rasool Allah ﷺ remained for about two or three years, unmarried.
So, it was a very difficult time on Muhammadﷺ.
Some scholars would say that there was wisdom in this happening, in the same time
and that is to increase the dependence of the Muslims on Allah.
So, rather than the message being protected by Abu Talib(ابو طالب),
and supported by Khadijah(خديجه),
now there would be more reliance on Allahسبحانه وتعالى, because there was no one else
no one around Rasool Allah ﷺ to give him that same support.
So, this would increase the Tawakkal(توكل) the trust that the Muslims have in Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
This is a comment that was given by some of the scholars.
Allahسبحانه وتعالى revealed the Surah(سورة) called Al-Ish'rah(اِلشْرَح).
And in that Surah(سورة), it says;
فَإِنَّ مَعَ الْعُسْرِ يُسْرًا۝
With difficulty comes ease.
Rasool Allah ﷺ went through this most tragic time in his life.
So, it was followed with one of the best blessings given to him by Allah.
Because of the size of the calamity, the bounty that followed it, was great.
Rasool Allah ﷺ narrates and this Hadith(حديث) is in Bukhari(بخاريْ) similar narrations are in Muslim(مسلم)
and in Masnad Imam Ahmad(مسند امام أحمد) in most of the books of Hadith(حديث), these narrations exist.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says,
while I was in Al-Hateem(ألحطيم) or Al-Hijr(ألحجر)
and this is the semi circle area close to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), which is part of the original building of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said that he was there at night.
The Messenger of Allah said,
I received a visitor, an angel, who came and opened my abdomen and pulled out my heart.
And then my heart was placed in a basin, golden basin, filled with faith, Eeman(ايمان).
And my heart was placed in it and washed and then stuffed and replaced.
And then I was presented an animal,
smaller than a horse, larger than a donkey.
Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) was narrating this Hadith(حديث).
And his students one of At-Tabaeen(ألتابعين), Al-Jarood(الجرود),
asked Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك), Is this animal Al-Buraak(ألبراق).?
Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) said: Yes.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: This animal would take a stride as far as it can see.
So, the Messenger of Allah is trying to describe to us the speed of this animal.
And Rasool Ullah described it as that this animal would place its hoofs at the extent of its sight,
it would take a stride as far as it can see, with one leap
it would wrap the distance equivalent to the distance you could see or look forward.
So, it was an extremely fast beast very fast, swift.
You just see the earth wrapping in front of you.
Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) told me to mount this animal and then he would guide me.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says, in another Hadith(حديث) that I was taken to
and this Hadith(حديث) is in Muslim(مسلم), this portion was not mentioned in the Hadith(حديث) of Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ),
you have bits and pieces of Al-Isra wal Miraj(ألإسراء و المعراج) mentioned in different Ahadith(احاديث)
in Muslim(مسلم) it says that Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) took me to Jerusalem.
And I tied my mount at the gates of Al-Masjid(مسجد)
and then I entered and prayed two Rakah(ركعة).
And it states that Rasool Allah ﷺ was an Imam(امام),
and the people who were following him were the Prophets.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said,
I was led by Jibreel(جبريل) up in the heavens.
He said, we made it all the way to the gates of the lowest heaven, the nearest heaven.
Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) knocked on the gates.
So, the gatekeepers said: Who is it?
Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) said, it is Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل).
And who was with you.?
Muhammad(محمد).
Was he given, his mission?
Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) said: Yes.
They responded by saying, he is welcome, and his arrival is a pleasure.
And they opened the gates
So, you can see no one can make it through unless, they have permission, they have clearance.
Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) being the angel of Allah, who was going up and down the heavens with Al-Wahee(ألوحي),
he told them, I am Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) so he can go through,
who's with you.? Muhammadﷺ!
Was he already given the mission.?
So, they didn't know yet that Muhammadﷺ was already a Prophet,
when they were informed, immediately they opened the gates and said, he is welcome.
And his arrival is a pleasure,
We're happy that he's here.
They opened the gates Rasool Allah ﷺ said, I went in and I found there in my father Adamعليه السّلام,
the Messenger of Allah said Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) introduced me to Adam(آدم) and said,
this is your father Adam(آدم). Greet him.!
So, I said, Assalam-O-Alaikum(اسلام عليكم).
Adam(آدم) saluted me in return and said, Walaikum Salam(وعليكم السلام)
and then Adamعليه السّلام said, welcome to my pure son. Welcome to the pure Prophet.
When I think of this meeting,
I try to imagine the pleasure and happiness that both the Prophets had.
You know, Imagine Adamعليه السّلام is meeting the brightest and greatest of his children, Muhammadﷺ.
He is meeting him for the first time, after thousands of years.
Now Adamعليه السّلام has a chance to meet his greatest son.
And imagine the surprise of Muhammadﷺ to meet his father Adam(آدم),
I mean imagine you have Adam(آدم) in front of you and you greeting him.
It must have been such a pleasurable moment
and they might have wished to sit down together and have a conversation.
But remember that Muhammadﷺ in this journey is on a tight schedule, he has a lot waiting ahead of him.
So, Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) carried Muhammadﷺ, and they went up to the gates of the second heaven.
They knocked same thing, they were asked Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل), who is with you.?
Muhammadﷺ! Is he a Nabi(نبي).?
Has he been given a Risalah(رسالة)?
They opened the gates, Muhammadﷺ said: I went in and I met Jesus and John, the two cousins,
Eesa(عيسى) and Yahya(يحيى).
Yahya(يحيى) is referred to, in the Christian literature as John the Baptist.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
And I exchanged greetings with them and what are the greetings of Islam, and the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء)?
Assalam-O-Alaikum(ألسلام عليكم), Peace be upon you, that's the greeting.
And then we moved ahead to the third heaven,
knocked on the gates, went through and I met with Joseph, Yusufعليه السّلام.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
وَاِذَا بِهِ اُوْتِيَ شَطْرَ الْحُسْن
He has been given half of beauty.
So, if you had the big block of beauty half of it was with Yusufعليه السّلام
We made it to the forth heaven, went through and I met with Idrisعليه السّلام
and Allahسبحانه وتعالى says;
وَرَفَعْنَاهُ مَكَانًا عَلِيًّا
We have elevated him to a very high status, he was in the fourth heaven.
We went to the fifth heaven and therein, I met with Haroon(هارون), Aaron, peace be upon him.
And then I went to the sixth heaven and I met Musaعليه السّلام,
and his meeting with Musa(موسى) was an eventful meetings, Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله)
always Musa(موسى) is surrounded with important events,
in Qur'an, one of the scholars said,
كَادَ الْقُرْآنُ اَنْ يَكُوْنَ مُوْسَى
Qur'an was almost going to be the story of Musa(موسى),
he's mentioned, so frequently therein
and his personality is so outstanding
Whenever the name of Musaعليه السّلام is mentioned there's something important going to happen.
Rasool Allah ﷺ passed by Musa(موسى),
Musa(موسى) started to weep after they greeted each other, and Musa(موسى) welcomed Muhammadﷺ.
Musa(موسى) started to weep,
when he was asked, How come you're weeping. He said,
غُلَامٌ بُعِثَ بَعْدِيْ يدخل مِنْ أمته اَلْجَنَّةْ اَكْثَرُ مِنْ اُمَّتِيْ
A young man was given Prophet hood after me,
and he will have more of his followers entering paradise than mine.
Up until, that moment, Musa(موسى) had the largest following of any Prophet.
The children of Israel(اسرائيل) were the largest believing nation up until that point,
but now there was a new world record,
by the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ.
So, Musa(موسى) wept, he cried,
and you can see that there is competition between the Prophets, ﷺ
but you will notice that it's not the competition of jealousy and envy.
It's a compassionate competition.
And you'll see that in the upcoming conversation between Muhammadﷺ and Musaعليه السّلام.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said and I moved up to the seventh heaven
and I went in and I met my father Ibrahim عليه السّلام and I exchanged Salaam(سلام) with him.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said, and then I was presented with Al-Bait-Al-Ma'amoor(ألبيت المعمور).
And in one narration, it states that Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) actually had his back, kneeling towards Al-Bait-Al-Ma'amoor(ألبيت المعمور).
What is Al-Bait-Al-Ma'amoor(ألبيت المعمور).?
Al-Bait-Al-Ma'amoor(ألبيت المعمور) has been mentioned in Qur'an.
وَالطُّورِ۝
وَكِتَابٍ مَسْطُورٍ۝
فِي رَقٍّ مَنْشُورٍ۝
وَالْبَيْتِ الْمَعْمُورِ۝
Allahسبحانه وتعالى is making an oath in the established house; Al-Bait-Al-Ma'amoor(ألبيت المعمور),
Al-Bait-Al-Ma'amoor(ألبيت المعمور) to the creation of the heavens is equivalent to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) to us.
Just as we make the Tawaf(طواف) around Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
and it is the first house on earth established for the worship of Allah.
The same thing is to be said about Al-Bait-Al-Ma'amoor(ألبيت المعمور).
So, as Muslims will visit Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), Angels will visit Al-Bait-Al-Ma'amoor(ألبيت المعمور).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says, Al-Bait-Al-Ma'amoor(ألبيت المعمور) is visited by 70,000 angels every day,
and they never come back to it again.
Do you understand the implications of that?
When Rasool Allah ﷺ says that every day a new group of 70,000 angels would visit the established house.
How many angels are there?
If on a daily basis, you have 70,000 Angels visiting it and they never come back again.
And for how long has this been going on?
For how many thousands or millions or billions of years?
So, you multiply all of those days by 70,000.
How many angels are there.
It puts us human beings to shame.
I mean, we're saying that we have over population on the Earth 6 billion of us.
Who are we compared to the world of the angels this massive creation.!
You know, Rasool Allahﷺ says;
أَطَّتِ السَّماءُ، وحُقَّ لها أن تَئِطَّ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; the heavens above you are moaning
and they are justified to moan because on every space equivalent to the size of four fingers,
there is an angel bowing down in Rakoh(ركوع)
or prostrating in Sujood(سجود), worshipping Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
all over the heavens above us.
Every position every area or volume equivalent to the size of four fingers is occupied by an angel, worshiping Allah.
So, this is a vast, huge creation
that makes us the world of the human beings seem insignificant.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
And by the way
in the narration that states that Ibrahimعليه السّلام was kneeling towards Al-Bait-Al-Ma'amoor(ألبيت المعمور).
It is symbolic to have Ibrahim عليه السّلام in that position after he passed away, sitting next to Al-Bait-Al-Ma'amoor(ألبيت المعمور)
because he was the one who built Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) on Earth.
So, when Allah took his soul away.
Allahسبحانه وتعالى had him rest next to Al-Bait-Al-Ma'amoor(ألبيت المعمور), the house of the angels.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I saw Sidra-Tul-Muntaha(سدرةالمنتهی).
I traveled further, and I reached to Sidra-Tul-Muntaha(سدرةالمنتهی)
Sidra-Tul-Muntaha(سدرةالمنتهى) is a loat tree, it's a tree.
But it is Al-Muntaha(المنتهى), Al-Muntaha(المنتهى) is the end.
So, it's the end of the heavens.
Beyond that you get into the world of the afterlife, you have paradise,
you have the throne of Allah, you have Al- Kursi(ألكرسي)
So, Sidra-Tul-Muntaha(سدرةالمنتهى) is the end of this universe created by Allahسبحانه وتعالى,
you have seven heavens one over the other.
And then after that, you have Sidra-Tul-Muntaha(سدرةالمنتهى), and then you get beyond that into different world.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ reached to that Sidra(سدره) and Rasool Ullah saw four Rivers emanating from it.
And he asked Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل), what are these four rivers.?
So, he was told, two of them are apparent and two of them are hidden.
The apparent ones are the Nile and Euphrates
and the hidden ones are the two rivers of paradise.
What it means by the Nile and the Euphrates?
Is that because these rivers are so blessed in this world, there is an equivalent of them up there.
And that tree is so close to paradise that you have two rivers of Paradise passing, from under it.
So again, you have the seven heavens one over another.
And then after that you have Al-Bait-Al-Ma'amoor(ألبيت المعمور), which is in the seventh heaven.
And then after that you have Sidra-Tul-Muntaha(سدرةالمنتهاء).
And then beyond that you get into the world of the paradise and the throne of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
"Now in terms of size,
the lowest heaven which we are in
compared to the heaven above it, is like a ring in a desert.
And the second compared to the third is like a ring in a desert.
And the third to the fourth is like a ring in a desert.
And on and on until we get to the sixth to the seventh.
It's like a ring in a desert.
And then the seventh heaven, compared to the Kursi(كرسي) of Allah, is like a ring in a desert."
Now this lowest heaven that we are living in, in terms of size
we don't even know how vast it is.
All of the known universe today is within the lowest heaven.
Because Allahسبحانه وتعالى says;
وَلَقَدْ زَيَّنَّا السَّمَاءَ الدُّنْيَا بِمَصَابِيحَ
We have adorn the lowest heavens with stars.
So, all of the stars are located within the lowest heaven.
And we haven't even been able to reach to the end of the creation of the stars.
Every now and then we're discovering new galaxies and new clusters and new stars.
So, it is a vast creation.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ had the chance to go through all of it, on that amazing journey.
After Rasool Allah ﷺ passed the Sidra-Tul-Muntaha(سدرةالمنتهی), this tree.
He went further, up
and he made it all the way until he met with Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
And that was the combination of this trip,
he reaches to the heights and he speaks to Allahعَزّوجَلّ, directly.
Allahسبحانه وتعالى prescribed on Muhammadﷺ Fifty(50) daily prayers.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
I descended and on my way back, I pass by Moses, Musaعليه السّلام,
who asked me, what did Allah tell you?
He said;
Allah has prescribed 50 daily prayers on my nation.
Musa عليه السّلام said: Your people will not be able to handle that.
I have tested people before you and I have experienced the children of Israel for a very long time.
Go back to your Lord and tell him to reduce it.
Tell him to relief you.
Muhammadﷺ followed this advice, senior advice
and he went back to Allahسبحانه وتعالى and told Him,
relief me of some of the prayers.
Allahسبحانه وتعالى reduced them by 10.
Muhammadﷺ went down,
Musa(موسى) said; what happened.?
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him, he said, go back.
Ask Allah to give you a further reduction.
Went back again 10 were reduced came down.
What happened?
Allah reduced it to 30, go back again.
Muhammadﷺ goes back another time.
They were reduced from 30 to 20.
Musa(موسى) tells him, go back again.
They were reduced from 20 to 10.
Musa(موسى) told Muhammadﷺ, go back another time.
Muhammadﷺ goes back, it was reduced to five.
He goes down reports it to Musa(موسى),
Musa صلى الله عليه وسلم says; O Muhammad(محمد) I know people,
I have experience, I haven't dealt with the children of Israel(اسرائيل), your nation will not be able to handle it.
Go back and tell Allah to reduce them further.
Muhammadﷺ said: I am so ashamed to go back to Allah and ask him for further reduction.
I cannot.
So, you can see the difference between the personality of Muhammadﷺ and Musa(موسى).
Musa(موسى) wouldn't have minded arguing with Allah further.
Musaعليه السّلام was the one, who asked Allahسبحانه وتعالى, I want to see You.
Allahسبحانه وتعالى has already given Musa(موسى) the favor of speaking to him.
Musa(موسى) wanted more.
Allah I want to see you and then obviously we know what happened, he collapsed.
Musa عليه السّلام is the one, who punched the angel of death and knocked his eye out.
So, Musa عليه السّلام was a very strong man and that was his personality
and Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah are all the same in their Da'wah(دعوة) but their personalities are different.
So, Muhammadﷺ did not go back
and he heard a voice saying that this is the prescription on you five daily prayers,
but you will receive the reward of 50.
Rasool Allah ﷺ made it back to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), on the same night.
Rasool Allahﷺ went to Umm Aimen(أم أيمن) and he told her about what happened.
He said, I've been to Jerusalem and back, in this night.
She said: O Messenger of Allah, do not tell anyone about that,
nobody will believe it.
It's impossible,
now Umm Aimen(أم أيمن) believed it
but she said that the people will not.
The Kuffar(كفار) of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) will not.
The journey towards Jerusalem used to take one month,
Rasool Allah ﷺ made it, within one night,
not only to Jerusalem but to Jerusalem back and he also went all the way to meet with Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Umm Aimenرضي الله عنها told him, do not tell your people about it.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I will,
I will convey the message, regardless of what the people will say.
It's part of my mission I will tell them what happened.
وَمَا عَلَيْنَا إِلَّا الْبَلَاغُ الْمُبِينُ
Your responsibility is to convey.
Rasool Allah ﷺ obviously realized the weight of this news and how difficult it will be.
So, he went out and was quiet and somber.
They started to speak to some people and the news reached to Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل).
And Rasool Allah ﷺ was sitting in the Masjid(مسجد), quiet
and worried about the consequences of this news.
So, Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) heard about it.
He came to Muhammadﷺ and said: O Muhammad, anything new
Muhammadﷺ said: Yes.
Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) said: What.?
Muhammadﷺ said: This night, I've visited Jerusalem and came back.
Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) said: Jerusalem.
Muhammadﷺ said: Yes.
Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) said: O Muhammad(محمد), if I would call your people right now and bring them here.
Would you tell them the same thing you just told me now?
Muhammadﷺ said: Yes, I would.
Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) happy and pleased, went running, calling people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
O people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) come forward and he gathered them and he brought them forth.
And when they're all present he told Muhammadﷺ;
O Muhammad(محمد), can you please tell your people what you just told me a moment ago.
Muhammadﷺ without any hesitation, he said:
I have been to Jerusalem and back, the previous night.
The narrator of the Hadith(حديث) says people started clapping, whistling, laughing they made a big joke out of it.
Imagine the crowds clapping, whistling, laughing and they were falling on each other.
So, some of the seasoned travelers among them, who knew Jerusalem and have been there,
asked Muhammadﷺ to describe the mosque, described Jerusalem to us.?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I started describing but then I became vexed,
I mean Rasool Allah ﷺ did not spend a long time there to remember every single detail of the place.
But then Muhammadﷺ said: Allah showed me the Masjid(مسجد) the mosque of Jerusalem right in front of my eyes
and I described it stone by stone, brick by brick.
And they said that he has given an accurate, excellent description.
But then there was something else that was mentioned in another narration by Ibn Is'haq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ).
When Muhammadﷺ was on his way back from Jerusalem to Makkah.
He passed by a caravan belonging to the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), at night.
And they have lost the camel of theirs
and Rasool Allah ﷺ because he was up in the air he was able to see it.
So, he called them and said that your camel is in this place.
Now they didn't know where the voice is coming from?
And then he drank some of their water.
And he also remember the description of this caravan,
he went back to Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and he told the people;
and other signs is that, this caravan belonging to you, they lost the camel,
and I gave them directions to it and you can ask them about it.
And also I drank some of their water in such and such container.
And the caravan is headed by a camel and he described the camel, describe the load on the camel.
So, they immediately sent out somebody to go and meet the caravan before it comes into Makkah.
It was still some distance away.
And the person found out the description to be accurate
and that they did lose a camel and they found it because they heard the voice coming from the sky
and also that they missed some of their water.
And these are all signs that were given to them but that wasn't sufficient for them to belief.
Now the story of Al-Israa wal Miraj(ألإسراء ولمعراج) was so difficult for some to handle.
It caused some of the weak Muslims to apostate,
it was such a difficult thing for them to grasp.
But that is the case with these amazing miracles that Allahسبحانه وتعالى would show, His Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء).
LESSONS TO BE LEARNED FROM AL-ISRAA WAL MIRAJ(ألإسراء ولمعراج).
Number one,
the event of opening the chest of Muhammadﷺ has occurred more than once.
It occurred once when he was with Halima Sadia(حليمه سعديه), when he was a child.
And it occurred another time in the journey of Al-Israa wal Miraj(ألإسراء ولمعراج)
by the way, the meaning of Al- Israa wal Miraj(ألإسراء ولمعراج) is Israa(اِسرَاء) means, traveling at night.
The meaning of Miraj(معراج) is ascending,
Israa(اِسرَاء) is traveling at night, Miraj(معراج) is ascending,
Israa(اِسرَاء) is the journey of Rasool Allah ﷺ from Makkah to Jerusalem.
Al-Miraj(المعراج) is the journey from Jerusalem to the heavens.
So, the event of opening the chest of Rasool Allah ﷺ happened more than once.
And these are two incidents, when it happened and it could have happened another time,
or more than once, in addition to these two occurrences.
Number two, the conversation of Rasool Allah ﷺ with Musaعليه السّلام,
when Allahسبحانه وتعالى prescribed 50 daily prayers on Muhammadﷺ, Muhammadﷺ accepted it.
But when he went down and met Musaعليه السّلام,
Musa(موسى) told him your nation will not be able to handle it.
So, Musa(موسى) is speaking out of experience and that is the value of experience.
Sometimes knowledge does not suffice, you have to have in addition to knowledge, experience,
Musa(موسى) told Muhammadﷺ, I have more experience than you do in dealing with the people,
you are new in this, I have spent my whole life,
dealing with the most difficult people, Bani Israel(بني إسرائيل),
believe me they won't be able to handle it, go back and ask for reduction.
Musa(موسى) himself learned this,
learn that experience, is different than knowledge.
When Musa(موسى) was meeting with Allahعَزّوجَلّ, when he went to meet with Allah, in the journey of the 40 days.
Allahسبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى) that in your absence your people have worshiped the calf,
وَمَا أَعْجَلَكَ عَنْ قَوْمِكَ يَا مُوسَىٰ َ
قَالَ هُمْ أُولَاءِ عَلَىٰ أَثَرِي وَعَجِلْتُ إِلَيْكَ رَبِّ لِتَرْضَىٰ َ
قَالَ فَإِنَّا قَدْ فَتَنَّا قَوْمَكَ مِنْ بَعْدِكَ وَأَضَلَّهُمُ السَّامِرِيُّ۝
Allahسبحانه وتعالى said that your people have went astray,
and they deviated due to the Samry(سامري),
and he made for them a calf out of gold.
So, Allah told Musaعليه السّلام everything that happened.
Musa(موسى) just received from Allah the 10 tablets, right, 10 tablets, Alal-Alwaah(على الوح).
So, Musa(موسى) had the tablets in his hand, and he was told by Allah that your people have deviated.
So, Musa(موسى) already knew, when Musa(موسى) went back
and he saw his people worshipping the calf.
What did Musa(موسى) do?
He threw the tablets from his hand.
Musaعليه السّلام already knew that how come his response was different when he saw it, compared to when he heard it.
Because seeing something is not like hearing it.
When Allah told him, that your people have deviated, Musa(موسى) had the tablets in his hands and nothing happened.
But when he saw it, with his own eyes, he threw the tablets, it was a surprise for him.
لَيْسَ الْخَبَرْ كَالمُعَايْنَه
When you see something is different than hearing it.
Musaعليه السّلام is telling Muhammadﷺ that I have dealt with the people, I have firsthand knowledge,
your people cannot handle this, it's too much.
And he kept on asking for reduction.
And when it was reduced to five, Musa عليه السّلا told Muhammadﷺ even five is too much for them.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) Musa(موسى) was right.
Musa عليه السّلام was right.
How many Muslims don't even pray the five daily prayers.?
How many of them laps and they would pray some and Miss others.
But May Allah reward Musa(موسى) for making it easy on us at least it was reduced to five,
if it would have been 50 imagine how difficult it would have been.
We're barely doing the five,
what would be the situation?
If we had to do 50,
so we owe it to Musaعليه السّلام
and we need to thank him, immensely for that.
When I said, that the competition between the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) is a compassionate competition.
Musaعليه السّلام even though he wept
when he knew that Muhammadﷺ has a larger following than his.
That didn't make him not giving us his advice, his valuable advice.
So, you can see how eager Musa(موسى) was to help us
and how eager Musa(موسى) was to give his advice to Muhammadﷺ.
So, they loved each other.
The Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) loved each other.
So, their competition was a competition of love of each other
Musaعليه السّلام, he kept on insisting and telling Muhammadﷺ go back and ask for reduction.
And when Musa(موسى) said that, he has more people entering Jannah(جنة) compared to me,
I think we already touched upon the visions
that Rasool Allah ﷺ had, on the Day of Judgment seeing the different nations of the prophets.
Some prophets have 10 followers, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
Some have five followers, I've seen a prophet with two followers.
I've seen a prophet with one follower,
and I've seen prophets with no followers at all.
Imagine a prophet coming on the Day of Judgment alone.
They spend their whole life in Da'wah(دعوة) no one responded, nobody
and then when he saw a huge nation, he thought that it is his following,
but then it turned out to be the following of Musa(موسى).
So, that's the greatest Ummah(امة) after the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ.
The third lesson, the importance of Salah(صلاة),
there is no command, none, whatsoever that was prescribed on us in heavens, except Salah(صلاة).
Every other Ibadah(عبادة), every other ritual that we have was prescribed on the earth.
Jibreel(جبريل) would reveal to Muhammadﷺ, the revelation on Earth with the exception of Salah(صلاة)
it was reserved to be given to Muhammadﷺ in this special one to one meeting between Allah and Muhammadﷺ.
Salah(صلاة) is so important that Allahسبحانه وتعالى prescribed it in a direct conversation
between Him and His Messenger Muhammadﷺ, without anyone in between.
Everything else was a revelation through Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل), with the exception of Salah(صلاة),
that just to show you how important Salah(صلاة) is.
Not only to Muhammadﷺ, even when Allah prescribed Salah(صلاة) on the people of Banni Israel(بني إسرائيل),
Allahسبحانه وتعالى prescribed Salah(صلاة) on Musa(موسى)
in the direct conversation that happened between Allah and Musa(موسى) in At-Toor(ألطور),
in the Ayaat in Surat Ta'ha(سورة طه)
إِنَّنِي أَنَا اللَّهُ لَا إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا أَنَا فَاعْبُدْنِي وَأَقِمِ الصَّلَاةَ لِذِكْرِي۝
I am Allah, there is no god besides Me.
so establish prayer in my remembrance.
And that was the moment in which Musa(موسى) became a prophet.
So, he was given the commands of prayer,
immediately when he became a prophet.
He was told first,
لَا اِلَهَ اِلَّا الله
and then second, to pray.
And that was when Musa(موسى) was at the age of 40, and he received the revelation from Allah,
when Allah spoke to him directly.
So, that's the value of Salah(صلاة)
Salah(صلاة) is the Ibadah(عبادة), in which Rasool Allahﷺ said: If the Muslim doesn't do it, they have left Islam.
بَيْنَ الْعَبْدْ وَالْكُفْرِ وَ الشِرْكِ تَرْكُ الصَّلَاةْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; Between a person and becoming a disbeliever is discontinuing prayers, not praying.
So, that's how important Salah(صلاة) is
not only is praying important, but even playing around with the time and not praying within the interval of time is a major sin.
The Ayah(آية) that says;
فَخَلَفَ مِنْ بَعْدِهِمْ خَلْفٌ أَضَاعُوا الصَّلَاةَ وَاتَّبَعُوا الشَّهَوَاتِ ۖ فَسَوْفَ يَلْقَوْنَ غَيًّا۝
Allahسبحانه وتعالى promised Hellfire to who.?
To the ones, who have lost their prayers.
Ibn Masood(ابن مسعود) gives an interpretation to this Ayah(آية).
He says losing their prayer does not mean that they don't pray,
but it means, they pray past time.
It is the opinion of Umar Ibn Al-Khattabرضي الله عنه
that if a person misses one prayer intentionally without an excuse,
they have left the folds of Islam.
Obviously the scholars have two opinions in regard to the Ahadith(احاديث) that state the disbelief of the one who doesn't pray.
But the end result is that prayer is the most important ritual in Islam.
It is the one thing no one is excused from.
If you don't have enough money, if you don't have the ability to make Hajj(حَجْ), you're excused.
If you are unable to fast,
because of old age or illness, you are excused.
If you don't have wealth, you do not have to pay Zaka'h(زكوة).
But there is no situation, where a person is excused from prayer.
If you can't pray standing up, pray sitting down
you can't pray sitting down, then you pray laying down.
You can't pray laying down because you are paralyzed or something, with your finger.
You can't do with your finger, with your eyes.
But there is no situation where a person is excused from praying.
Even when the battle is going on Salah(صلاة) still has to be done.
In the Ayaat(آيات) of Salat-Ul-Khauf(صلاة الخوف).
So, Salah(صلاة) is the only Ibadah(عبادة) in Islam where there is no excuse of not doing it.
There is no relief of it, it has to be done.
The scholars have said that the Muslim who is spying on the enemy and cannot pray.
This is our classical scholars, they said; such a person can pray with their finger.
But they have to pray. Salah(صلاة) needs to be done.
Number four,
this journey reveals to us the importance of the Holy Land, Jerusalem and its surroundings.
Allahسبحانه وتعالى says; Surat-Ul-Isra'a(سورة الإسراء):
سُبْحَانَ الَّذِي أَسْرَىٰ بِعَبْدِهِ لَيْلًا مِنَ الْمَسْجِدِ الْحَرَامِ إِلَى الْمَسْجِدِ الْأَقْصَى الَّذِي بَارَكْنَا حَوْلَهُ لِنُرِيَهُ مِنْ آيَاتِنَا ۚ
إِنَّهُ هُوَ السَّمِيعُ الْبَصِيرُ۝
Exalted is He, Who took His servant by night, from Al-Masjid-Ul-Haraam(مسجدالحرام) in Makkah
to Al-Masjid-El-Aqsaa(مسجدالاقصى), the furthest mosque in Jerusalem,
whose surroundings We have blessed.
Allahسبحانه وتعالى says that that's a blessed land to show him of Our signs.
Allah has shown Muhammadﷺ many signs on this journey,
He is the hearing, the seeing.
Jerusalem was promised to the believers,
Ibrahimعليه السّلام was given that promise that your descendants, the believers among them,
will be the guardians of Jerusalem, the Holy Land.
And that was the promise that was fulfilled through the prophets of the children of Israel.
Allahسبحانه وتعالى also promised Jerusalem to Musaعليه السّلام,
now even though Musaعليه السّلام, Moses did not see the result of that promise in his lifetime,
but it occurred in the lifetime of his successor,
Yousha Bin Noon(يوشى بن نون), the Prophet Joshua.
And the children of Israel remained in that land,
as long as they were the bearers of truth.
And when they deviated from the true message of Allah and they fought the prophets
and they attempted to kill Jesus عليه السّلام and they killed other prophets,
Allahسبحانه وتعالى stripped away the land from them, and gave it to the other branch, the descendants of Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل).
Allahسبحانه وتعالى gave that to Muhammadﷺ and his Ummah(امة)
because now there are the ones, who are carrying the torch of truth.
So, that land is promised to the believers.
And since now the torch is being carried by the seal of the prophets, Muhammadﷺ,
even though Muhammadﷺ will not open Jerusalem in his lifetime, but he must visit it.
He must go and receive the keys.
And the symbolism in this journey of Rasool Allah ﷺ going to the Masjid(مسجد)
and leading the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) in a prayer
is to show that now Muhammadﷺ is the inheritor of the message of the prophets
and he is a leader on the sons of Adam(آدم).
And the land that was under the custodianship of the prophets of Banni Israel(بني اسرائيل)
is now transferred to the followers of Muhammadﷺ.
And just as Musa(موسى) did not see it in his lifetime, but it happens in the lifetime of his successor Joshua.
Muhammadﷺ did not see it in his lifetime.
And it happened in the time of Umar Ibn Al-Khattabرضي الله عنه.
The man, whom Rasool Allah ﷺ said; If there's a prophet after me, it would be Umar(عُمَر).
So, that was a blessing that Allah reserved for Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب).
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), look at the divine destiny, when the Muslims reached to the Gates of Jerusalem
even though, the religious and political leadership of Jerusalem couldnot fight the Muslims and they had to give it up.
They said, We will surrender.
But we cannot surrender to anyone but the Khalifah(خليفه) of the Muslims,
he must come here and take the keys with his own hand.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله)
that brought out Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) to travel all the way from Madina to Jerusalem,
because he is the one, who will receive the keys of Jerusalem.
And he went all the way there and he was the one who was given the keys, to the Holy city.
So, now the Muslims are the ones, who have the promise of Allah, the promise of the Holy Land, Bait-Ul-Muqaddas(بيت المقدس).
Number five,
which we mentioned
فَإِنَّ مَعَ الْعُسْرِ يُسْرًا
With difficulty comes ease.
Rasool Allah ﷺ went through some very difficult moments in the 10th year of His revelation.
So, Allahسبحانه وتعالى gave him this blessing, the journey of Isra'a-Wal-Miraj(ألإسراء ولمعراج)
and Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), this was such a treat for Muhammadﷺ.
I mean, there is no tourist journey with so many attractions, as this journey of Isra'a-Wal-Miraj(ألإسراء ولمعراج)
and to have Jibreel عليه السّلام as your guide, to take you through,
and to meet with the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah
and to go in this journey to the real Wonderland from one place to another and then you enter into paradise, Jannah(جنة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ in that journey, he entered into Jannah(جنة) and he saw the river of Al-Kausar(الكوثر), which was given to him.
Jibreelعليه السّلام told Muhammadﷺ, this is your river, Al-Kausar(ألكوثر).
So, it's also such a bounty that Allahسبحانه وتعالى has given Muhammadﷺ
and that would bring back what we mentioned earlier that you never know what Allahسبحانه وتعالى is hiding for you.
Hajar عليها السّلام we mentioned that when she was running between As-Safa-Wal-Marwa(ألصفاء ولمروة),
she didn't know, she was crying at the time,
she didn't know that this would be followed by the greatest nation the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ.
So, when you're going through difficulties in this world, you don't know what Allah is reserving for you.
When Allahسبحانه وتعالى says;
فَإِنَّ مَعَ الْعُسْرِ يُسْرًا
With difficulty comes ease, believe in that promise,
with every difficulty, you go through Allahسبحانه وتعالى is reserving for you something.
Whether you get it in this world or the afterlife, you're going to get it.
So, the Muslim should never give up,
should never feel despair.
The sixth lesson the position of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر).
How did Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) received the news of Al-Israa-Wal-Miraj(ألإسراء ولمعراج).
When the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), were joking around laughing, clapping, whistling,
Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) was not present
and he was coming into Makkah and someone went and told him. Do you know what happened?
Muhammadﷺ claims that, he went to Jerusalem and he made it back.
Now, what do you think the response of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was?
Well, he did believe but what did he say?
That's an important thing to add.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: If he said it, then it's the truth.
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) did not just accept the information that was given to him.
He said, If he said it, it is the truth.
there's two things to learn from the first segment, if he said it,
and that is the science of verifying Hadith(حديث),
when our scholars study the lives of the narrator's of the Hadith(حديث),
they want to discern whether Muhammadﷺ said it or not,
you were not just going to accept anything that is said, by anyone out there.
We want to make sure that Muhammadﷺ did say it.
And that is, what makes a difference between us and the people of the book
the people of the book, have accepted pretty much everything that came down, to them,
even if it was separated from the original source by a few centuries.
So, it is a blind faith, it is following Zhan(ظن), conjuncture.
But with the Muslims, no, they had the science of verification
where they studied the lives of thousands and thousands of men and women
to look at their profile whether these are truthful person, people or not,
whether we can accept, what they convey or not.
So, when people go back to Islamic sources, they can feel at ease
that they are dealing with material that has been verified.
اِنْ كَانَ قَالَهَا فَقَدْ صَدَقَ
If he said it, then it is the truth.
So, that is the science of verifying Hadith(حديث).
The second part is, then it is the truth.
And this is the characteristic of Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه
and that's why, he was called As-Siddique(اَلصَّدِيق), the believer.
Whatever Rasool Allah ﷺ says; I will believe him.
I have faith in him, I have faith in everything that he says.
Finally, it's terminology issue.
When we use the word heavens or heaven, it confuses some to think that we are referring to paradise.
Now that's a problem with the English language that these are synonymous heaven and paradise.
But in Islamic terminology, they're not.
Heaven is talking about the sky above us.
That is part of the temporary world that will be destroyed on the Day of Judgment.
Paradise is referring to Jannah(جنة),
Jannah(جنة) is the permanent place of abode for the believers.
So, whenever I'm using the word Heaven, I am not referring to paradise, I'm referring to the sky above us.
I will use as a translation Jannah(جنة), paradise.
So, I hope this confusion is not in the mind of any one of you.
Because I mentioned that the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) are in the different Heaven.
This is not talking about paradise, it's talking about meetings that occurred with the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء),
in the heavens above us that are lower than paradise.
Now that Rasool Allah ﷺ has lost the protection of his uncle, Abu Talib(ابو طالب).
And his efforts of Da'wah(دعوة) in Makkah were being blocked.
He tried to search for other alternatives.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ made a journey to At-Taef(ألطائف).
And he accompanied with him, Zaid Bin Harissaرضي الله عنه.
They went to At-Taef(ألطائف)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ went to the leaders of At-Taef(ألطائف),
Rasool Allah ﷺ, that's his method, he would go to the leaders of the community,
He would enter the house from the gate.
He went to meet the leaders of At-Taef(ألطائف), the tribe of Thaqeef(ثقيف).
And these were three brothers
He presented the message to them and asked them for support and help.
Now these three men responded in a miserable way.
The first one of them said;
اَنَا اَمْرُط كِسَاَء الْكَعْبَهْ اِنْ كَانَ الله قَدْ اَرْسَلَكْ
I'm going to tear apart the clothing of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), if Allah has sent you as a prophet.
The clothing of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) was sacred to them.
So, he is saying that I'm going to tear it apart
if Allah has sent you as a prophet.
The second among them said, his statement was, did not God find anyone better than you to send?
I mean, Isn't there anybody out there better than you?
And the third one said, I cannot speak to you.
I just can't speak to you, because if you are a messenger from Allah, as you claim,
then you are such an important person.
And I don't think that I'm qualified to speak to you.
And if Allah has not sent you as a messenger, and you are lying, then it's not appropriate for me to speak to a liar.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ, heard their response, he said;
Well, if you don't want to accept my message, at least
keep this conversation that we had, secret, keep it private.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not want the news to reach to Makkah that he has been turned down by the people of Thaqeef(ثقيف),
because it will only add to the persecution of the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), towards the Muslims.
So, he said keep it private
but they were such evil men and rude.
What they did is, they went to the fools among them and their slaves and their servants
and they asked them to go and revile Muhammadﷺ and scream at him and
imagine these crowds surrounding Muhammadﷺ, pelting Muhammadﷺ and Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه), with rocks,
screaming at them yelling, chasing them away.
Rasool Allah ﷺ and Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه) had to run out of At-Taef(ألطائف).
And Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه), he was protecting the body of Muhammadﷺ,
shielding him from the rocks that the people of Thaqeef(ثقيف) are throwing.
And they took refuge, they took shelter in a farm that belonged to two men from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), Ibn Rabiyyah(ابن ربيعه).
So, they went into this farm and they finally got away from the fools of the Thaqeef(ثقيف)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ was exhausted
his feet were bleeding.
And he was hurt because of the way he was treated by the people of Thaqeef (ثقيف).
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), Allahسبحانه تعالى sent down help on Muhammadﷺ, he was very hungry at that time.
The two owners of the farm who belong to Makkah.
They told their servant Addaas(عداس), who was a Christian.
They told him go and take some grapes and give it to Muhammadﷺ,
they felt sympathy for Muhammadﷺ, even though they were two of his staunch enemies
but now when they are in a foreign land in different territory,
they felt sympathy towards Muhammadﷺ, they decided that we should stand up for our tribesman,
we should stand up for Muhammadﷺ.
So, at least let's give him these grapes.
So they sent Addaas(عداس) and they told him take this plate of grapes and give it to Muhammadﷺ.
Addaas(عداس), he carried the grapes and he went to Muhammadﷺ and he presented it to him.
Muhammadﷺ said بسم الله, in the name of Allah and he said it loudly.
Addaas(عداس) was surprised.
And he asked Muhammadﷺ, he said;
These words are not said by people in this land.
Arabs, people in this area don't speak these words.
The Messenger of Allah, from these words of Addaas(عداس)
was able to imply that he's a foreigner and he might be following a different religion.
So, he told Addaas(عداس), where are you from, and what is your religion?
And Rasool Allah ﷺ used to ask any people he would meet, where are you from.?
So, he told Addaas(عداس) where are you from, and what is your religion.?
Addaas(عداس) responded by saying, I am a Christian man from Ninawa(نينوى), Ninawa(نينوى) in Iraq.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said, so you are from the village of the pious man, Younas Ibn Matta(يونس إبن مته),
Johna Son of Imatae, Prophet of Allah.
Addaas(عداس) said; And how do you know about Johna son of Imatae,
Muhammadﷺ said: He is my brother.
He was a prophet and I'm a prophet.
When Addaas(عداس) heard that he immediately bent down and started kissing the feet of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and then he kissed his hands and head.
Now the two owners of the farm, from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
when they saw that they looked at each other and said, Look, he has already corrupted our slave.
Muhammadﷺ would Da'wah(دعوة) wherever he is.
And these two men who felt sympathy towards Muhammadﷺ are now regretting it.
We sent in, our slave to take some fruit to him and he has corrupted our slave.
When Addaas(عداس) came back, they told him What's wrong with you?
How come you were kissing his feet, hands and head?
He said on all Earth, there is no man finer than him.
He told me something that no one other than a prophet can know.
They told him; Don't let this man make you leave your religion
because your religion is better than his.
Now what did the two sons of Rabiya(ربيعة) know about Christianity,
but it is Kuffr(كفر) that is in their heart that will make them say whatever, would deceive the people.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ